A colour analogue photograph,
10.2 x 15.2 cm,
horizontal format,
depicts her smiling.
I’m not sure who captured her, but I still own the point-and-shoot Charman AW-750 camera, a ’90s relic I keep as memorabilia.
Her lips,
slightly tinted blue,
hint at where my anemia came from,
and so do the two sweaters she’s wearing, despite what appears to be late spring;
everyone else in the photo is wearing summer clothes.
This is the only known photograph of her outside the apartment,
before the police began knocking on doors and escorting people to the border.
In all other photographs, taken later, she is sitting on her couch, either staring at the camera or chasing me.
I am usually out of frame or blurred, unaware that, in the register of the nation-state, our roles have been swapped.
Only, she is not blurred;
she is invisible.